A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Commission for the Arts, 1968-2022
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Commission for the Arts, 1968-2022
The Library of Virginia
36089, 37698, 42160, 43771, 44617, 45445, 51953, 53791
32.3 cu. ft. (40 boxes)
LVA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 36089, accessioned 6 November 1998.
Accession 37698, accessioned 13 October 2000.
Accession 42160, accessioned 9 September 2005.
Accession 43771, accessioned 30 May 2008.
Accession 44617, accessioned 1 December 2009.
Accession 45445, accessioned 14 March 2011.
Accession 51953, accessioned 29 December 2016.
Accession 53791, accessioned 9 January 2023.
Historical Information
The Virginia Commission for the Arts and Humanities was established as an agency of state government in 1968 and is mandated to support and stimulate excellence in all the arts, in their full cultural and ethnic diversity, and to make the arts accessible to all Virginians. Toward this end, it provides financial assistance for arts activities and information/advisory services to artists, arts organizations, and others interested in the arts. The Commission’s funds come from the Virginia General Assembly and the National Endowment for the Arts, a federal agency. The name of the agency was changed to the Virginia Commission for the Arts (Record Group 152) in 1979.
The agency is guided by thirteen commissioners appointed to five year terms by the Governor and confirmed by the General Assembly. At least one commissioner is appointed from each congressional district. The Commission employs a staff to implement programs and policies and is also assisted by several advisory panels.
Major issues of interest to the commission include artistic quality, access to the arts, cultural diversity, assistance to individual artists, and development of arts organizations. Six Regional Advisory Panels, the Arts Education Advisory Panel, the Touring Advisory Panel, and Artist Fellowship Panels review and evaluate applications for grant funds with these major issues in mind. These grant funds go toward general operating support, technical assistance, local government challenge, touring assistance, artist fellowships, writers programs, residency programs, teacher assistance programs, and arts curriculum development. In addition to grants, the commission also provides information and advisory services.
Scope and Content
Records of the Virginia Commission for the Arts include correspondence, subject files, grants lists, and minutes that document the planning, direction, and implementation of agency programs and are evidence of actions and policy decisions. Also includes board books/packets given to board members each board meeting. Note that there is some duplication between accessions.
Accession 37698, Delmarva Folklife Project records, 1997-1999, inncludes the following reports: Final report for Fieldwork Year 1: October 1997-September 1998; Final Report for Fieldwork Year 2: November 1998-October 1999; Latino Cultural Survey, 1998-1999; and Hispanic Arts and Narratives, Fieldwork, January-July 1999.
Accession 45445: Minds Wide Open Open Program files, 2010, document the Women in the Arts program activities sponsored by the Minds Wide Open Program of the Virginia Commission for the Arts. This statewide celebration included special public programs and events including plays, choreography, compositions, and exhibitions of painting, films, and photography, etc., that were held across the Commonwealth to honor the contributions of women in the arts. Records include the final report of the program and several binders of news releases, news clippings, photographs, brochures and programs related to Women in the Arts events.
Accession 51953 includes Board packets, 1968-1971, 1973-1974, 1990-1995 Jan, 1997-2015; Publications and Tour Directories, 1992-2014; Press releases and press clippings, 1984-1992; and Correspondence and subject files, 1970-2014, including information on bylaws and policy, board committees, strategic planning, Arts in Virginia study, Women’s Project, Minds Wide Open Program, Virginians for the Arts, Writers in Virginia Program, Governor’s Arts Awards, Go Fish Project, Heritage Awards, and National Endowment for the Arts partnership agreements.
Accession 53791 (2.5 cu. ft.) includes Board books/packets, 2014-2022; Minutes, 1978-2000; Awards files, 2000-2009.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Records
Contents List
- Series I. Records, 1968-2015.
  - Grants and Minutes, 1968-1998 (Accession 36089)., 1 cu. ft. (1 box)
    This accession is arranged in chronological order.
    - Listing of grants, 1969-1994. (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1968-1998. (Box 1)
  - DelMarva Folklife Project Records, 1997-1999 (Accession 37698)., .1 cu. ft. (1 box)
    - Delmarva Folklife Project records - Final report for Fieldwork Year 1, 1997 Oct-1998 Sept. (Box 1)
    - Delmarva Folklife Project records - Final Report for Fieldwork Year 2, 1998 Nov-1999 Oct. (Box 1)
    - Delmarva Folklife Project records - Latino Cultural Survey, 1998-1999. (Box 1)
    - Delmarva Folklife Project records - Hispanic Arts and Narratives, Fieldwork, 1999 Jan-July. (Box 1)
  - Grants and Minutes, 1994-2005 (Accession 42160)., 1 cu. ft. (1 box)
    - Listing of grants, 1994-2005. (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1998-2005. (Box 1)
  - Grants and Minutes, 2005-2007 (Accession 43771)., .35 cu. ft. (1 box)
    - Listing of grants, 2005-2007. (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 2005-2007. (Box 1)
  - Grants and Minutes, 2007-2009 (Accession 44617)., .35 cu. ft. (1 box)
    - Listing of grants, 2007-2009. (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 2007-2009. (Box 1)
  - Minds Wide Open Program records, 2010 (Accession 45445)., 2 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
    This accession is arranged in no discernable order.
    - Minds Wide Open Program files, 2010. (Box 1)
    - Minds Wide Open Program files, 2010. (Box 2)
  - Records (Minutes, board books and Correspondence and subject files), 1968-2015 (Accession 51953)., 25 cu. ft. (25 boxes)
    - Board books and minutes, 2014-2015. (Box 1)
    - Board books and minutes, 2012-2013. (Box 1a)
    - Board books and minutes, 2009-2011. (Box 2)
    - Board books and minutes, 2007-2008. (Box 3)
    - Board books and minutes, 2005-2006. (Box 3a)
    - Board books and minutes, 2003-2004. (Box 4)
    - Board books and minutes, 2001-2002. (Box 5)
    - Board books and minutes, 2000-2001. (Box 5a)
    - Board books and minutes, 1998-1999. (Box 6)
    - Board books and minutes, 1992-1995 Jan, 1997. (Box 7)
    - Board books and minutes, 1968-1971, 1973-1974, 1990-1991. (Box 8)
    - Tour Directories (Dance, Music, Opera, Theater), 2006-2009. (Box 9)
    - Tour Directories - Notebooks, 2013-2014. (Box 10)
    - Tour Publications, 2005-2013. (Box 10)
    - Tour Publications - Art Works for VA, 2006-2014. (Box 10)
    - Tour Publications, Directories, Guidelines and Brochures - Governor's Arts Awards, 1992-2002. (Box 11)
    - Tour Publications - Guidelines, 1992-2002. (Box 12)
    - Writers in Virginia, 1995-2000. (Box 13)
    - Minds Wide Open - Women in the Arts, 2010. (Box 13)
    - National Endowment for the Arts Partnership Agreements, 2006-2011. (Box 14)
    - National Endowment for the Arts Partnership Agreements, 2002-2006. (Box 15)
    - The Arts in Virginia - Study, 1979. (Box 16)
    - VALC Study Committee, 1978-1979. (Box 16)
    - Minutes, 1973-1974. (Box 16)
    - Governor's Arts Awards, 2000-2001. (Box 16)
    - Virginians for the Arts, 1992. (Box 16)
    - Budget cuts, 2010FY. (Box 16)
    - Legislation, 2010. (Box 16)
    - Office of the Governor, 2002-2006. (Box 16)
    - Office of the Governor, 2006-2010. (Box 16)
    - Office of the Governor, 2010-2014. (Box 16)
    - Travel and the Arts, 1970. (Box 16)
    - Old Dominion Symphony Council, 1971-1972. (Box 16)
    - Women's Project, 1982-1984. (Box 17)
    - The Arts in Virginia Study, 1979. (Box 17)
    - Bylaws, 1993. (Box 17)
    - Policy/Budget Committee, 2005-2010. (Box 17)
    - Legislative Committee, 1993-1997. (Box 17)
    - Lewis House, 1983-1990. (Box 17)
    - Task Force on Local Arts Agencies, 1995-1996. (Box 18)
    - Governor's Arts Awards, 2000-2001, 2008. (Box 18)
    - Virginians for the Arts, 1992, 1996-1997, 1999-2001, 2003-2005. (Box 18)
    - Commission meeting notes, 2008-2009. (Box 19)
    - Public Relations workshop, 2005. (Box 19)
    - Strategic Planning, 2004-2007. (Box 19)
    - Virginia Symphony, 2010. (Box 19)
    - Go Fish, 2001. (Box 19)
    - The Fourth R, 2000. (Box 19)
    - Majors, 2007-2008, 2010. (Box 19)
    - Heritage Awards, 2009. (Box 19)
    - Board meetings, 2007. (Box 20)
    - Minds Wide Open, 2012. (Box 20)
    - Minds Wide Open - First Ladies, 2009-2012. (Box 20)
    - Policy Commitee, 2007. (Box 20)
    - Press Releases, 1987-1989. (Box 21)
    - Press Releases and other historical information, 1984-1992. (Box 22)
  - Records (Board books, minutes, awards files), 1978-2020 (Accession 53791)., 2.5 cu. ft. (8 boxes)
    This accession is arranged in chronological order within type of record.
    Include board books, minutes, awards files and photographs.
    - Board book, 2014 Mar 26. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Board book, 2014 Oct 1. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board book, 2015 Mar 25. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Board book (Part I), 2015 June 10-11. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Board book (Part II), 2015 June 10-11. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Board book, 2015 Sept 30. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board book, 2015 Dec 8-9. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Board book, 2016 Mar 30. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Board book (Part I), 2016 June 15-16. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Board book (Part II), 2016 June 15-16. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Board book, 2016 Sept 28-29. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Board book, 2016 Dec 8. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Board book, 2017 Apr 4-5. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Board book, 2017 June 14-15. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Board book, 2017 Sept 28. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Board book, 2017 Dec 7. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Board book, 2018 Apr 4. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Board book (Part I), 2018 June 13-14. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Board book (Part II), 2018 June 13-14. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Board book, 2018 Sept 27. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Board book, 2018 Dec 6. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Board book, 2019 Mar 27-28. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Board book (Part I), 2019 June 10-11. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Board book (Part II), 2019 June 10-11. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Board book, 2019 Oct 2. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Board book, 2019 Oct 3. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Board book, 2019 Dec 12. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Board book, 2020 Mar 19. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Board book (Part I), 2020 June 16-17. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Board book (Part II), 2020 June 16-17. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Board book, 2020 Oct 1. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Board book, 2020 Dec 9-10. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Board book, 2021 Mar 24-25. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Board book, 2021 June 16-17. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Board book, 2021 Oct 6. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Board book, 2021 Oct 7. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Board book, 2021 Dec 8-9. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Board book (Part I), 2022 June 15-16. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Board book (Part II), 2022 June 15-16. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 1979-1980. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 1981-1982. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 1983-1984. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 1985-1986. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 1987-1988. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Minutes, 1989-1990. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Minutes, 1991-1992. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Minutes, 1993-1994. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1995-1996. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Minutes, 1997-1998. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Minutes, 1999-2000. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, 2001-2002. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Minutes, 2003-2004. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Minutes, 2005-2006. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Minutes, 2007-2008. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Minutes, 2009-2010. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Minutes, 2011. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Governor's Awards for the Arts, 2000. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Governor's Awards for the Arts, 2000. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Governor's Awards for the Arts, 2008. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Awards for the Arts, 2008. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Heritage Awards, 2009. (Box 8, Folder 5)